<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>innovation on shekispeaks</title><link>https://sheki.in/tags/innovation/</link><description>Recent content in innovation on shekispeaks</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 May 2020 20:08:40 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sheki.in/tags/innovation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Movies I liked—2020</title><link>https://sheki.in/post/movies_i_like_2020/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 17:13:39 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://sheki.in/post/movies_i_like_2020/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="blindspotting">Blindspotting&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A poor white man in Oakland struggles with his identity as the
city gets gentrified. David Diggs weaves gracefully weaves hiphop into the
story. I enjoy movies set in San Francisco bay area but Most movies set here
are caricatures (internship). This is a movie captures a bit of the zeitgeist.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="women-at-war-icelandic">Women at War (Icelandic)&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>It is the story of an eco warrior who brings down
electric lines to rebel against the system and how she gets help form an anti
establishment sheep farmer. Watch it as an adventure drama with a unique setting
rather than a movie about ecology or saving the planet. Crisp and sharp—not a
single bit of overacting; very not American.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="vast-of-night">Vast of Night&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>It is a Science fiction movie about aliens set in Cayuga, New
Mexico, yes near Roswell, in the 1950s with two high school students as the
leading characters. The movie was very very very stylistically shot. I do not
much about America before the 2010s and Vast of Night I feel gave me a little
glimpse of post war booming USA. My write up here does a poor job of telling how
great the movie is—just go watch it.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-trial-of-the-chicago-7">The Trial of the Chicago 7&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A movie about the famous trial of some protesters
during the Democratic convention in the late 1960s. It was mostly entertaining
and I learnt some history.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="nothing-fancya-documentary-about-diana-kennedy">Nothing Fancy—a documentary about Diana Kennedy&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I browse, read and buy a lot of cookbooks and in that process learnt that Diana
Kennedy was the mother of Mexican food writing. In the documentary a ninety plus
year old Diana tells her life story. At that age she drives around, cares
immensely about food and runs cooking classes. She is a force of nature. Diana’s
life was full of decisive action—getting out of boring Britain, coming to Latin
America, not having kids, exploring food and understanding the culture. She did
not plan a career around Mexican food but that’s where her interests led her.
She is a template for how to not lead a cookie cutter life.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Donate to end hunger in India</title><link>https://sheki.in/post/donate-to-end-hunger-in-india/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Dec 2020 14:57:45 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://sheki.in/post/donate-to-end-hunger-in-india/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the book &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Shadow-Sun-Ryszard-Kapuscinski/dp/0679779078">The Shadow of the Sun&lt;/a> , the Polish author journalist Ryszard Kapuscins talks about the poor people in Lagos Nigeria struggling through extreme hunger. These people were living meal to meal and sleeping the rest of the time to save energy so that they could make do with the little food they could get, they had no energy to do anything else and were stuck in this eternal struggle for food. Initially I found that world of 1960s Nigeria distant and unreal—my brain processed it as fiction. But soon, I realized that it was as real today as back then. I thought about the thousands of street kids suffering malnutrition that I saw in India growing up. I remembered their thin limbs begging for money every time I stopped at a traffic signal. I felt a visceral need to do something about it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My first reaction to the problem was that I should set up canteens that serve free nutritious food to the needy and poor, not unlike the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Langar_(Sikhism)">Langars of the sikh faith&lt;/a>. But soon I got bogged down in the details—how to reach the poor and how to fund the canteens. Since I am in no way capable of running a food operation I decided to donate to charities that have a better grasp of the problem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Finding charities that work on solving hunger in India was not straightforward. &lt;a href="https://www.givewell.org/">Givewell&lt;/a> did not rate any Indian charities. Looking at some of the charities that came up as top search results, I was discouraged by their focus on the fundraising efforts—fundraising banquets at Taj or building mobile apps for the donors. It was difficult to find data about the efficiency of Indian charities. A note by a Givewell evaluator sums the situation well&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>“I was told by one organization that its measure of success is ‘the percentage of children who complete the program who do not enter prostitution.’ However, “completing the program” was defined as those who did not drop out of the program before the age of 21 and were settled and married. In other words, it seems that only success cases are included in the success rate. Unsurprisingly, the organization claimed a 100% success rate on this metric.”&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>This is when I realized that to make progress, I need to find charities that have a good enough solution and not the best solution and I found a couple:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.akshayapatra.org/">Akshay Patra&lt;/a> is a charity that distributes free meals to kids via schools. They have 52 kitchens in India and are mostly an urban operation. They have found that central kitchens in urban areas and automation helps them bring down the costs. They have not found the same cost benefits in rural areas. Overall the model seems simple, raise money and feed kids meals via their school programs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.salaambaalaktrust.com/">Salam Balaak&lt;/a> started out as a daycare centre for street children but realized that a safe space is the most critical need for children from poor families. They operate residential shelters for poor kids where they also provide the poor kids with nutritious meals. They operate four residential homes for poor kids and also run an open shelter program where the kids stay with their families but can come to the open shelter for food and some space. The Salaam Baalak solution focuses more on the end to end outcomes for kids and focuses on living and meals. They only operate in New Delhi right now. This solution is perhaps more effective but is difficult to scale up to the millions of poor kids in India.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Reading books about places I have not been to, so often stirs so many different emotions in me and sometimes, like today, these emotions inspire action. This holiday season I urge you to read about places and people you know nothing about and to donate to charities that work to help the poor in the developing world.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can &lt;a href="https://sheki.substack.com/">follow me on substack&lt;/a> to receive these posts via email.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Spreadsheet—a personal history</title><link>https://sheki.in/post/spreadsheet/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2020 16:23:55 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://sheki.in/post/spreadsheet/</guid><description>&lt;p>When I was a kid, I created a game of cricket in a spreadsheet program called Lotus 1-2-3. Each die roll would represent a ball being bowled in a cricket game, and the number told me what happened —a batter got out, or scored a run. I kept rolling the die and entering the numbers onto the spreadsheet and in course simulated a game of cricket. My cricket universe within the spreadsheet tracked statistics—batting averages and strike rates for all the players. I spent an equal amount of time playing the game and improving the spreadsheet.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The first evidence of humans using something akin to a spreadsheet comes from ancient Sumeria. Archeologists have found stone tablets etched with tables tracking some form of accounts. Accountants before the advent of the computer, used to maintain ledgers that were spreadsheets on paper. These had one major disadvantage over the electronic version—if you had to rewrite, recalculate or etch over the entire table if a single value changed. If you were maintaining the accounts of a coffee shop and the price of coffee went up that meant days of tedious boring work to create a new copy of the sheet.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Electronic spreadsheets solve this by using a concept of “references”. A cell can contain a formula that references a value stored in another cell. So if you update the value of the cell containing the price of coffee beans, the whole spreadsheet updates instantaneously. This was the key insight in the predecessor of the modern spreadsheet called LANPars. It was a programming language that would output a sheet.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>VisiCalc was the first incarnation of the modern spreadsheet in a design we recognize.
VisiCalc was a clunky program with green and black flickering cells but it had the numbered rows and alphabetical columns that we now find in all modern spreadsheets. VisiCalc was a raging success. People bought the two thousand dollar Apple II to run the hundred dollar VisiCalc. Small stores started to do their accounts in VisiCalc. Dan Bricklin the inventor of VisiCalc was actually worried that the accountants would soon be out of a job.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As a professional software engineer my first duel with spreadsheet was when I was working at Bright—a solar energy startup that was selling solar panels in Mexico city. The company had been around for six months when I joined. Pablo the head of operations, built the company by using spreadsheets as duct tape. To generate a quote sales people would enter some numbers into a sheet and it would spit out the price, the engineer on site would record the size of the roof on another sheet and that would trigger an alert to our back office where folks started procuring panels of the correct size. At that point, I did not have a lot of respect for the spreadsheet, I thought it was clunky, error prone and a tool suited for non programmers. I had just heard about the Blue whale fiasco at JP Morgan London where an incorrect formula in a sheet lead to a wrong risk calculation of the deal that lead to a loss of a billion dollars for the bank. Pablo complained to me that the spreadsheets had become too slow. I started to build a website to provide the same features as the sheets. Each sheet took me two weeks to build out. I had to reinvent things like the capability to upload files and display PDFs that Google sheets provided out of the box. I had eleven of these sheets to copy over. As I was working on the problem, sales wanted to change the formula for discounts. Everyone knew how to modify the spreadsheets, but only I could change the software. That&amp;rsquo;s when I realized how accessible spreadsheets had become, almost everyone knew how to use one and it helped them get their job done faster. Spreadsheets were increasing productivity for everybody.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Back to the Apple II, the VisiCalc was so popular that in typical silicon valley fashion competitors started to clone it. The most successful clone was Lotus 1-2-3. It was named 1-2-3 as it was “as simple as one two three”. It was a highly polished version of VisiCalc, less clunky and could take advantage of the larger memory available on newer computers and it would run on the upstart operating system—Microsoft DOS. To top all of this, Lotus 1-2-3 was the first software to be advertised on TV. VisiCalc stopped selling overnight. But the buccaneer spirit of the valley was not to be satiated. Borland, another software company, released a competitor to Lotus 1-2-3 cheekily called Quattro or four. To lure users from Lotus, Borland built compatibility mode that would let Quattro operate Lotus files, it even had the same menu options in the same order as Lotus 1-2-3. This infuriated lotus and they went to the court. After six years the court decided in favour of Borland, by providing an analogy to the VCR—“The buttons on a VCR are used to control the playback of a video tape, similarly menu commands are used to control the 1-2-3 file. Since the buttons are essential to the operation of the VCR their layout cannot be copyrighted.”&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My next major encounter with the spreadsheet professionally was when I was working for a shipping logistics company. I was the lead of a team building software to predict the price of shipping a container on a route—say from HongKong to Los Angeles. The benchmark to beat was a spreadsheet created by one of the Vice President’s of the company. The legendary spreadsheet and the acumen of its creator was one of the companies competitive advantage. The software we built was compatible with spreadsheets from day one. Business associates could update the prices by uploading a spreadsheet into software. They had a manual mode to always override the software generated values. This time I deferred to the powers of the spreadsheet. My lesson here was it is foolish to try to replace the spreadsheet everywhere, it does a lot of small things for a lot of people in a lot of different ways. People have all these neat automation tricks in their spreadsheets that they do not tell you when you do user interviews to build a better replacement for the sheets. It’s second nature to them, they are familiar with the interface, they know the keyboard shortcuts and it is fast.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Borland vs Lotus fight did not matter much because Microsoft soon released Microsoft Excel. By the time version 5 of Excel was released in 1993, bundled in the office suite, it was the clear market leader. For the next fifteen or so years, Excel and spreadsheets meant the same thing. People started using Excel in ways its designers did not envision —schools were using it to arrange seating layouts and doctors were using it to calculate the correct dosage of anesthesia before a surgery. The accountants did not lose their jobs as more businesses wanted to simulate many “What If” cases—what if we hire 100 more people, what if we give out a smaller bonus, what if we acquire that company. It was the finance industry that Excel transformed the most. Deals were made by exchanging models built in Excel. Today there is an Excel world championship where analysts duke out to find who is the best at using Excel.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The next big jump in spreadsheet technology came around when Google launched the online version of it by cobbling together technology acquired from a few startups. By 2010, Google had made the spreadsheet collaborative—multiple folks could edit a single spreadsheet in real time—and on top of it Google made it free. Pablo’s spreadsheet process only worked because multiple people could update the information about a single customer in real time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Joel Spolsky who was a famous program manager for Microsoft Excel, claims that in his user studies he saw that the most common use case for Excel was to record lists. During the me too movement, a clerk at one hollywood company created a spreadsheet list of media men who had abused women. This list was updated by women anonymously. This led to investigations and sometimes firing of senior media mein in firms like NPR, Buzzfeed and New Yorker.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It is fashionable to say that “software is eating the world” in Silicon valley. Spreadsheet is leading the charge on this front by finding uses in all industries. Software now is chewing on what Excel has already masticated. Nate Silver used Excel to create the models and the charts to usher in the new field of data journalism. Spreadsheets are the de facto tool to collect data in academia. A recent paper analyzed three thousand genetic papers and found that one in five papers had an error due to a common error—the gene “Septin 2” which is shortened to “SEPT 2” automatically becomes “2-Sept” in Excel and the whole calculation goes for a toss. There are full RPG games made inside of Excel. Gym trainers share workout routines by sharing a spreadsheet. Casinos use it to optimize slot machine layouts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I use spreadsheets to plan my finances, to coordinate bachelor parties and to create fancy charts to make a point at work. The creators of the spreadsheet did not build a program to solve a single problem, they built a general purpose tool that improved productivity. Spreadsheets made money for Micorosoft and other companies but provided a lot more value to society. Good software is never a zero sum game.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Spreadsheet is a powertool. Its design has been copied over many times by different companies. In a world where the trend seems to be about building good looking single purpose software that scales well perhaps the option of building general purpose tools that look and feel the same across industries is an opportunity worth investigating.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Croatia trip report</title><link>https://sheki.in/post/about_croatia/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 15:05:13 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://sheki.in/post/about_croatia/</guid><description>&lt;p>I recently spent a week in Croatia.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Croatia was part of former Yugoslavia. Yugoslavia was ruled by Joseph Tito, a
communist dictator. I saw a huge bomb shelter in the city center in Zagreb.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When the Yugoslavia split up in the 1990s, Croatia became an independent country.
The next door neighbor, the partly Muslim Bosnia bore the brunt of the war. The
BBC documentary &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oODjsdLoSYo">Death of Yugoslavia&lt;/a>
is explains the war in great depth.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We spent a lot of time in the island of Vis. It is a beautiful island with great
beaches. Vis till 1989 was controlled by
the Yugoslav army. This meant no tourists were allowed on the island. The military
airstrip there now is a great winery. The town of Komiza is the local fisherman
village. A lot of Komiza people escaped to the US during the World War.
They settled in San Pedro in California, as fisherman.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We saw a church called &amp;ldquo;Our Lady of the Pirates&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I am not sure if something was
lost in translation. Surprisingly during WWII,a remarkable Canadian captain supplied
the Yugoslav partisans by pirating German supply ships. The captain attributed a
good part of his success to the blood-curdling threats uttered by the Yugoslav
partisan who manned the loud speaker.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I highly recommend renting a scooter and driving to different beaches on Viz.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The movie Mama Mia was shot on the Island of Viz. In the movie it is shown to be
an island in Greece, but Croatia apparently is cheaper.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The city of Split, was a Roman city and then a Venetian city. Unlike Zagreb
it was never really a Austro-Hungarian city. The Roman emperor Diocletian from Split, was
the last of the generation on non christian Roman emperors. People still live
in the old city. It was hair tickling to walk on streets built in the 3rd century.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Krka waterfalls was overrated and perhaps could be skipped for any other
beach town.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="food">Food&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Croatia has a lot of sea food. I had great Calamari everywhere. They have
amazing olive oil and sea salt. Peka is delicious slow cooked dish made with Octopus.
They have tasty Anchovies and Sardines. Burek is a pastry filled with spinach
or cheese. Ajvar is a pepper relish that provides some flavor relief. Cevapi
is a sausage dish usually served with Ajvar. There a few different local wines
available in Croatia, they are mostly dry. The whites are better than the reds.
The cuisine is simple, but the high quality ingredients make up for it. Spit roasted lamb is
a speciality of the districts further away from the sea.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Konobo Robinson in Viz was my favorite restaurant of the trip.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>TV/Movie gems from rest of the world</title><link>https://sheki.in/post/great_shows_and_movies/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2019 18:40:27 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://sheki.in/post/great_shows_and_movies/</guid><description>&lt;p>The Internet is great as it lets me watch great TV shows from all over the world
all over the world. These shows teach me a thing or two about the history and culture
of these places. Here are a few of my favorites:&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="a-very-secret-service-france">A Very Secret Service (France)&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Its a French spy TV show set in the 1960s. Its very stylish and acknowledges the sexism in the
workplace openly. France and its institutions had extremely low confidence right after WW2 and the
show captures this world. The spy agency and its boss grab on to all the elements of pre war colonial
French institutions. The have an avid respect for the old school &lt;code>General&lt;/code> (referring to de Gaulle).
The public opinion in France is split on the Algerian secession. The spy agency though tries its best
to defame the Algerian freedom fighters. In one episode a few agents are sent on a mission to recover
an atomic bomb from Algeria. This refers to the testing of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gerboise_Bleue">Gerboise Bleue&lt;/a>
by the French in the Algerian Sahara. There is an episode based on the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martel_affair">Martel Affair&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The show is funny, but not a comedy. Its Tarantino like retelling of
history inaccurately by design but still eye opening.
Its available on Netflix.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="midnight-diner-japan">Midnight Diner (Japan)&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This is a Japanese anthology TV show. Each episode takes place in a diner that opens at midnight. The non glamorous but working class clients
tell their story to &lt;code>Master&lt;/code> the chef. Each episode if focused on a dish the diner orders.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I found out Japan has female cab drivers and thats considered normal. The Japanese treat the Koreans and their food as inferior. People in Japan are very rounded compared to those in America. People have strong attachments to their parents. The show is low key and makes you wish more things in life were &amp;ldquo;low key&amp;rdquo;. This is my favorite show of the list.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Available on Netflix.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="comrade-detective-romania">Comrade Detective (Romania)&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Comrade detective is a buddy cop series. The premise is that the show was ordered by the Romanian communist government in 1980s to instill communist values. The dialogue is dubbed in English and makes it farcical by design. In one of the episodes there was a huge consignment of jeans are being smuggled to Romania. This made me think that most people in the world did not have jeans till the mid 1990s.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Available on Amazon Prime video.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="death-of-stalin">Death of Stalin&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Death of Stalin is a comedy documentary style movie about the power struggle after Stalin&amp;rsquo;s death. I learned how big a figure was the WW2 winning general Zhukov in the Soviet politburo. His support was crucial in Kruschev toppling Beria for power. The movie captures the fear of Stalin amongst his subordinates well. Jason Isaac&amp;rsquo;s for Zhukov and Steve Buschemi for Kruschev were great casting picks.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Bye Bye Facebook.</title><link>https://sheki.in/post/bye_bye_facebook/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Nov 2015 10:48:23 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://sheki.in/post/bye_bye_facebook/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is a copy of my Goodbye message I posted internally at Facebook.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Monday, (Nov 16) is my last day at Facebook.I was looking at the goodbye posts former People of Facebook for inspiration for my post. But instead, I decided to generate a message from the awesome corpus there.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This computer generated artisanal message mostly captures what I want to say:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So i really want to take this opportunity to say, after 4+ years of wonderful journey, the coming monday (nov-16) will be my last day at facebook.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve been a wonderful experience. Everyone i’ve worked with here truly cares about what is next in life. I have royally fucked up.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I feel sorry that I will never would have been able to doordash in. It is, of you all the facebook kool-aid. I&amp;rsquo;ll be strangers! the new friends around in the apartment. It&amp;rsquo;s user-base by mass and it won’t change how to stay cool. Wherever it is no immediate plans, i’m incredibly hard to analytics.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We all across the future where I decided to mobile-first. I absolutely fine without working on the company 4.5 years at facebook. Please don&amp;rsquo;t be a stranger.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be who i am today if i hadn&amp;rsquo;t gone through the many refactors i did. There is so many good friends. Facebook is truly an incredible place to work.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I &amp;rsquo;ll be moving up to san francisco.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Before i joined facebook, the goal was to get to this point. After about 6.5 years, it’s time for me to find some job in vietnam. I hope to take a part of sleep that no one of you will.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I am also incredibly smart and i’m really.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>/end of generated message.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Here is my code &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/sheki/19c4f439dfbae074df00">https://gist.github.com/sheki/19c4f439dfbae074df00&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I wish people expressed their feelings in a standardized way using JSON or GraphQL.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A conversation to remember.</title><link>https://sheki.in/post/a_conversation_to_remember/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2015 00:18:43 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://sheki.in/post/a_conversation_to_remember/</guid><description>&lt;p>I sometimes wonder, why I blog but it is to often to tell myself a story. Time
erodes your memories and you just have big events in your brain, but sometimes
it is the small things that happen to you which you enjoy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So today I republish a post of mine from 2009. I was an intern at
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_University_of_Berlin">Freie Universität&lt;/a> in
the great city of &lt;strong>Berlin&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A couple of days ago I met a Sri Lankan man at the bus stand as it is my habit
nowadays to speak to all people who look Indian. We got a bit chatty and we had
a lively discussion, and the conversation quickly veered towards LTTE and Sri
Lanka. This man a Tamil himself, he told me that his grandfather was a Chettiar
from Tamil Nadu who had moved down to Sri Lanka to set up a business, surprised
me by stating that he did not sympathize with the LTTE one bit. As the
conversation began to get more and more intense he said that LTTE kidnapped kids
and brainwashed them and trained them to wage the Elam’s war. It hit me that
this was no different than Taliban or any other Muslim military outfit. He
explained that the situation was grim back in Ceylon ( interestingly he reffered
Sri Lanka as Ceylon always) and the LTTE used to kill people even Tamils who did
not see eye to eye with their cause. He said that his family moved out of Sri
Lanka in the 70s to Canada and Germany.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At this juncture I asked him what about Prabhakaran, he plainly said Prabhakaran
has escaped with his close group of supporters and claims by the Lankan Army
reports are nothing but propaganda. I pushed him a bit more on how can he be
confident on the fact that Prabhakaran is alive, and he gave me a quick grin and
said that he knew a lot of people in Lanka and no one believes he is dead, well
I was surprised that Vellupillai Prabhakaran had such an indefatigable image in
the minds of the people.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I asked him does he not sympathize with the Tamilians of Sri Lanka, and he said
that the Tamils were big headed people (he himself was a tamil), who do not
respect the other people. He gave me an example saying that in the small Sri
Lankan community in Berlin, Tamils never spoke to any Non Tamils whereas the
Singhalese (the other ethnic group of Sri Lanka) people spoke to everyone and
were very accommodating. He himself while growing up in Sri Lanka had a lot of
Singhalese friends and not many Tamil friends.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As the conversation headed towards India, and I explained to him saying that
India is growing economy and a very vibrant place ( I have got used to doing
this as the Europeans have a portrait of India as a very poor third world
country where millions starve without food). He just slashed me down by saying
in India the things are fast and fun, in the west (he referred to Europe) the
things are slow but effective.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Our conversation got more and more lively but I had to get down at my bus stop
and wished him good bye may be for ever, as I do not have his name or contact.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I was delighted to know a lot about my neighboring country what the people think
there, how they feel about India. I got to know that you get a better picture of
the nation by speaking to some one from there than from some news articles. I
was surprised to meet a Sri Lankan who did not sympathize with the LTTE, who did
not like the attitude of the Tamils, who thought Prabhakaran was a terrorist and
is still alive.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I guess this is a post for me to remember this conversation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Originally at &lt;a href="https://shekispeaks.wordpress.com/2009/05/24/a-conversation-to-remember/">https://shekispeaks.wordpress.com/2009/05/24/a-conversation-to-remember/&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Surathkal</title><link>https://sheki.in/post/surathkal/</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2014 18:11:23 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://sheki.in/post/surathkal/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ravan">Ravan&lt;/a>, the king of Lanka and the
main antagonist of the Hindu epic &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ramayana">Ramayana&lt;/a>
was an ardent devotee of &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shiva">Shiva&lt;/a>.
Sometime before the main events of Ramayana unfolded, Ravan prayed to Shiva
and got hold of a powerful relic - &lt;em>Atma Lingam&lt;/em>. (demons
praying to gods and getting powerful relics / boons is a recurring theme in
Hindu mythology). Shiva though, places a condition, that Ravan has to carry the
Atma Lingam, without putting it down on the ground, until he reaches home -
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lanka">Lanka&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The rest of the gods worry that Ravan would become immensely powerful and
hard to defeat. The gods hatch a plan to ensure that Ravan puts the
AtmaLingam on the ground before reaching Lanka. &lt;a href="htps://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ganesh">Ganesh&lt;/a>
Shiva&amp;rsquo;s son - agrees to carry out the scheme.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As Ravan is passing by &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gokarna">Gokarna&lt;/a>, in
modern day Karnataka, India - the gods hide the sun. Ravan believing that it is
dusk, wants to prey as is his routine. Precisely at that point he is
approached by Ganesh, disguised as a priest. Ravan asks the priest to hold
the AtmaLingam while he prays for a bit. Ganesh, agrees albeit with a condition
that he will call his name three times, if Ravan does not respond, he will place
the AtmaLingam on the ground. Ravan agrees and proceeds to pray. Ganesh
places the AtmaLingam on the ground, without calling out thrice. He basically
cheats.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The relic now on the ground cannot be moved. Ravan is devastated and tries to
lift the AtmaLingam, but it won&amp;rsquo;t budge.
His force breaks a piece of the head of the Lingam. This piece falls a few
hundred kilometers southwards.
The place where the stone falls is called Sirathkal
(meaning head stone) in the local Tulu language.
Ravan obviously goes back home dejected.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In modern times Sirathkal is known as Surathkal, a suburb of
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mangalore">Mangalore&lt;/a>. I spent four years
studying Computer Engineering there at
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Institute_of_Technology,_Karnataka">NITK Surathkal&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I am curious about how places get their names, this was the story of Surathkal.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/1467558/surathkal.jpg" alt="Surathkal">&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>