<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mythology on shekispeaks</title>
    <link>http://sheki.in/tags/mythology/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Mythology on shekispeaks</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://sheki.in/tags/mythology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Surathkal</title>
      <link>http://sheki.in/post/surathkal/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2014 18:11:23 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sheki.in/post/surathkal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ravan&#34;&gt;Ravan&lt;/a&gt;, the king of Lanka and the
main antagonist of the Hindu epic &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ramayana&#34;&gt;Ramayana&lt;/a&gt;
was an ardent devotee of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shiva&#34;&gt;Shiva&lt;/a&gt;.
Sometime before the main events of Ramayana unfolded, Ravan prayed to Shiva
and got hold of a powerful relic - &lt;em&gt;Atma Lingam&lt;/em&gt;. (demons
praying to gods and getting powerful relics / boons is a recurring theme in
Hindu mythology). Shiva though, places a condition, that Ravan has to carry the
Atma Lingam, without putting it down on the ground, until he reaches home -
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lanka&#34;&gt;Lanka&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the gods worry that Ravan would become immensely powerful and
hard to defeat. The gods hatch a plan to ensure that Ravan puts the
AtmaLingam on the ground before reaching Lanka. &lt;a href=&#34;htps://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ganesh&#34;&gt;Ganesh&lt;/a&gt;
Shiva&amp;rsquo;s son - agrees to carry out the scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Ravan is passing by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gokarna&#34;&gt;Gokarna&lt;/a&gt;, in
modern day Karnataka, India - the gods hide the sun. Ravan believing that it is
dusk, wants to prey as is his routine. Precisely at that point he is
approached by Ganesh, disguised as a priest. Ravan asks the priest to hold
the AtmaLingam while he prays for a bit. Ganesh, agrees albeit with a condition
that he will call his name three times, if Ravan does not respond, he will place
the AtmaLingam on the ground. Ravan agrees and proceeds to pray. Ganesh
places the AtmaLingam on the ground, without calling out thrice. He basically
cheats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relic now on the ground cannot be moved. Ravan is devastated and tries to
lift the AtmaLingam, but it won&amp;rsquo;t budge.
His force breaks a piece of the head of the Lingam. This piece falls a few
hundred kilometers southwards.
The place where the stone falls is called Sirathkal
(meaning head stone) in the local Tulu language.
Ravan obviously goes back home dejected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In modern times Sirathkal is known as Surathkal, a suburb of
&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mangalore&#34;&gt;Mangalore&lt;/a&gt;. I spent four years
studying Computer Engineering there at
&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Institute_of_Technology,_Karnataka&#34;&gt;NITK Surathkal&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am curious about how places get their names, this was the story of Surathkal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/1467558/surathkal.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Surathkal&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>